Inventory of the Edwin Meese papers, 1941-1991
Hoover Institution Archives
Edwin Meese papers,
1941-1991
91005
Hoover Institution Archives
772 manuscript boxes, 2 oversize boxes, 1 envelope, 5 sound cassettes, 2 motion picture film reels (325.0 linear feet)
Speeches, correspondence, memoranda, reports, schedules, press releases, legal documents, printed matter, photographs, and sound recordings related to California politics and administration of the California state government during the governorship of Ronald Reagan; and to American domestic policy, Republican Party politics, and federal administration of justice during the presidency of Ronald Reagan. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Meese, Edwin.
Access
The collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Use copies of some sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. To listen to other sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1991, with increments received in subsequent years.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Related Materials
Ronald Reagan subject collection, Hoover Institution Archives
Citizens for Reagan records, Hoover Institution Archives
Governor and the Students videotape series, Hoover Institution Archives
Lee Edwards papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1931 December 2 Born, Oakland, California
1954-1955 Served in the United States Army
1953 A.B. in public administration, Yale University
1958 J.D., University of California, Berkeley Married Ursula Herrick
1959-1967 Deputy district attorney, Alameda County, California
1967-1968 Legal affairs secretary (previously called secretary on clemency and extradition) to Governor Reagan
1969-1974 Executive assistant, chief of staff to Governor Reagan, Sacramento, California
1975-1976 Vice president, administration, Rohr Industries, Chula Vista, California
1976-1980 Attorney at law
1977-1978 Director, Center for Criminal Justice Policy and Management, University of California, San Diego
1977-1981 Professor of law, University of California, San Diego
1980 Chief of staff and senior issues advisor, Ronald Reagan Presidential Campaign
1981-1985 Counselor to President Reagan, Washington, D.C. Member of President Reagan's Cabinet Member of the National Security Council
1983 Recipient, Distinguished Public Service Award
1985 February-1988 August U.S. attorney general, Washington, D.C.
1988- Distinguished visiting fellow, Hoover Institution, Stanford University, California Ronald Reagan Chair in Public Policy, The Heritage Foundation
1992 Author, With Reagan: The Inside Story
1996 President, Council for National Policy
1996-2004 Member, Board of Visitors, George Mason University
1997 Author, Making America Safer
2001-2013 Chairman, Center for Legal and Judicial Studies, Heritage Foundation
2004 Author, Leadership, Ethics and Policing
2006 Member, Iraq Study Group
2008 Named honorary Reagan fellow of Eureka College, Illinois
2012 Recipient, Bradley Prize
Scope and Content of Collection
The Edwin Meese papers document Meese's role in the gubernatorial and presidential administrations of Ronald Reagan. The collection contains speeches, correspondence, memoranda, reports, schedules, press releases, legal documents, printed matter, photographs, and sound recordings related to California politics and administration of the California state government during the governorship of Ronald Reagan; and to American domestic policy, Republican Party politics, and federal administration of justice during the presidency of Ronald Reagan.
Meese began his work for Ronald Reagan during Reagan's two terms as governor of California. In his book With Reagan, Meese notes that he was recommended to the governor based on his experience with law enforcement. From 1967 to 1968, Meese served as legal affairs secretary, tasked with resolving issues of extraditions, prisons, and capital punishment, as well as acting as a liaison to legal, judicial, and law enforcement departments. From 1969 to 1974, Meese was executive assistant and chief of staff, directing the governor's executive office and serving on the cabinet. In this role, Meese also had responsibilities concerning the National Guard, the Office of Emergency Services, and the Office of Criminal Justice Planning. The Gubernatorial Administration of Ronald Reagan File documents Meese's work during this period through correspondence, clippings, memoranda, reports, schedules, speeches, and court documents.
During Reagan's campaign for the presidency in 1980, Meese served as chief of staff and senior issues advisor. In order to devote more time to the campaign, Meese spent less time teaching as a professor of law at UC San Diego and gave up his duties managing the Center for Criminal Justice Policy and Management. After Reagan was elected, Meese served as a counselor to the president and as a member of his cabinet.
Boxes 566 to 582 document the Iran-Contra Affair, a scandal involving the sale of arms to Iran in exchange for Iran's help in releasing American hostages. In November 1986, after news of the scandal became public, Meese announced that some of the money gained from selling arms to Iran had been used to fund the Contras in Nicaragua. The collection includes clippings, correspondence, memoranda, testimony of Meese and others, phone logs, and chronologies related to the Iran-Contra Affair.
From February 1985 to August 1988, Edwin Meese held the position of attorney general of the United States. In this role, Meese influenced policy initiatives concerning drug abuse, civil rights, and criminal procedure, in addition to creating a national marijuana eradication program. His accomplishments included prevention and control of crime, improvement of the criminal justice system, protection of civil rights, promotion of economic growth, improvement of the legal system, government financial integrity, and the preservation of constitutional values. The Presidential Administration of Ronald Reagan File documents Meese's work during Ronald Reagan's presidency from 1981 to 1988, including his efforts as the 75th attorney general of the United States.
As required by law, security-classified materials have been removed from the collection until they can be declassified by government officials.
Arrangement Statement
The collection was acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1991, and this initial accession, boxes 1-127, was arranged into seven groups: Biographical File, Speeches and Writings, White House Office File, Department of Justice Office File, Subject and Historical File, Sound Recordings, and Photographs.
The majority of the collection was received as an increment to this original accession. The incremental materials, boxes 128-774, have not been arranged, and the original order and titles have been retained. The materials are divided into two major groups based on Meese's service to Ronald Reagan during Reagan's terms as governor of California and president of the United States. The Index to Major Groups can serve as a guide to the incremental materials in the collection.
Index to Major Groups
Gubernatorial Administration of Ronald Reagan File, 1941-1976.
Contains correspondence, clippings, memoranda, reports, schedules, and court documents related to Meese's role during Ronald Reagan's terms as governor of California. Boxes 128-554, 772-773, film shelf.
Agriculture and Services Agency
Boxes 349-353, 364-367
Appointments to government positions
Boxes 481-487
Budget
Boxes 312-335
Business and Transportation Agency
Boxes 370-378
California Council on Criminal Justice (CCCJ)
Boxes 160-170
Clippings
Boxes 456-480
Community and minority relations
Boxes 191-193
Conference file
Boxes 288-300
Correspondence and memoranda
Boxes 144-149, 154-155, 501-505, 529
Department of Corrections
Boxes 390-395
Education
Boxes 193-201, 487-494
Emergencies and disaster planning
Boxes 176-190
Energy
Boxes 440-446
Environment
Boxes 424-439
Health and Welfare Agency
Boxes 378-387, 552
Intelligence
Boxes 494-497
Intergovernmental management
Boxes 206-217, 247-251, 300-311
Legal affairs, legislation, and crime
Boxes 217-240, 264-271
Military
Boxes 240-247, 259
Office of Economic Opportunity
Boxes 395-408
Omnibus Crime Control and Safe Streets Act
Boxes 170-174
Photographs
Box 771
Schedules of Reagan and Meese
Boxes 255-261, 509-511
Sound recordings
Box 773
Speeches and speaking engagements of Meese
Boxes 511-515
Speeches of Ronald Reagan
Boxes 280-286
State employees
Boxes 357-364
Student radicalism, activism, and unrest
Boxes 230-236, 488-490
Tax reform
Boxes 338-348
Water
Boxes 447-449
Welfare
Boxes 409-418
Presidential Administration of Ronald Reagan File, 1975-1991.
Contains correspondence, clippings, memoranda, reports, schedules, and court documents related to Meese's role during Ronald Reagan's presidency, including Meese's service as attorney general from 1985 to 1988. Boxes 554-771, 774.
Alphabetical file
Boxes 563-566, 608-627, 644-658, 693-701, 736-769
Chronological file
Boxes 627-629
Clippings on Iran
Boxes 710-716
Correspondence
Boxes 602, 690-692, 708
Drug prevention
Boxes 585-596
Iran-Contra Affair
Boxes 566-581
Republican National Committee
Boxes 686-689
Ronald Reagan Presidential Foundation
Boxes 729-736
Schedules of Reagan and Meese
Boxes 554-556, 559-561, 582-584, 599-600, 603-608
Speeches and travel file
Boxes 706-708, 653-658
Reagan, Ronald.; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); United States. Department of Justice.; Audiotapes.; California--Politics and government--1951-; Justice, Administration of--United States.; United States--Politics and government--1981-1989.
- Biographical File, 1981-1988 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Interviews, press releases, and printed matter relating to the life of Edwin Meese III, arranged by physical form.
  - Interviews, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Interviews, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Interviews, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Press releases, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Printed matter, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1985 June-July (Box 1)
    - 1985 August (Box 1)
    - 1985 September (Box 1)
    - 1985 October (Box 1)
    - 1985 November (Box 1)
    - 1986 February (Box 1)
    - 1986 March (Box 1)
    - 1986 April (Box 1)
    - 1986 July (Box 1)
    - 1986 September (Box 1)
    - 1986 October (Box 1)
    - 1986 November (Box 1)
    - 1987 January-August (Box 1)
    - 1988 February-March (Box 1)
    - 1988 July-August, Typescript. (Box 1)
  - Coleman, Kate, "The Roots of Ed Meese," Los Angeles Times, 1986 May 4 (Box 1)
- Speeches and Writings, 1981-1988 (Boxes 1-37)
  Transcripts of speeches and interviews, rough drafts and printed copies of writings, brochures, charts, clippings, correspondence, handwritten notes, leaflets, map, memoranda, press releases, printed matter, programs, outline, and schedules, arranged in chronological order.
  - "The Transition to a New Administration," speech delivered at a dinner in honor of the Hoover Institution's Board of Overseers given by the Hoover Institution at the Sheraton-Carlton Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1981 January 6 (Box 1)
  - Remarks to the Promis Users Group Meeting, Shoreham Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1981 April 22 (Box 1)
  - Remarks to the California Sheriff's Association, San Rafael, California, 1981 April 27 (Box 1)
  - Remarks made in a question and answer session with foreign reporters at United States Information Agency's Foreign Press Center in Washington, D.C., 1981 May 12 (Box 1)
  - Delaware Law School commencement speech, Widener University, Delaware, 1981 May 16 (Box 1)
  - Notes for a fundraiser dinner speech for St. Paul's Manor Convention Center, Vacation Village, Mission Bay, 1981 May 23 (Box 1)
  - University of San Diego Law School commencement address, San Diego, California, 1981 May 24 (Box 1)
  - Remarks, Time Magazine luncheon for European businessmen, "F" Street Club, Washington, D.C., 1981 June 1 (Box 1)
  - Draft of commencement address, Naval War College, Newport, Rhode Island, 1981 June 24 (Box 1)
  - Speech, American Bar Association Criminal Justice Luncheon, New Orleans, Louisiana, 1981 August 11 (Box 1)
  - Speech, Oakland-Dalian Friendship Society, Oakland, California, 1981 August 27 (Box 1)
  - Remarks, Citizens for the Republic fundraiser dinner in honor of Edwin Meese III, Beverly Hilton Hotel, Beverly Hills, Los Angeles, California, 1981 September 11 (Box 2)
  - Speech, Sacramento Host Breakfast, Woodlake Quality Inn, Sacramento, California, 1981 September 11 (Box 2)
  - Speech and press conference, Concordia College Centennial Dinner, Bronxville, New York, 1981 September 23 (Box 2)
  - Speech given before the Senior Executives Association, Arlington, Virginia, 1981 September 24 (Box 2)
  - Guest appearance, special dinner at the Cuyamaca Club organized by the San Diego Coalition, 1981 September 25 (Box 2)
  - Address, California Savings and Loan League, Hotel del Coronado, San Diego, California, 1981 September 25 (Box 2)
  - Address, San Diego State University College of Business Luncheon, Sheraton-Harbor Island Hotel, San Diego, California, 1981 September 25 (Box 2)
  - Remarks, The Business Council, Hot Springs, Virginia, 1981 October 9 (Box 2)
  - Speaker, Aero Club Lunch, Army and Navy Club, Washington, D.C., 1981 October 14 (Box 2)
  - Remarks, Twelfth Annual Leadership Conference sponsored by the Center for the Study of the Presidency, Westin Hotel, Cincinnati, Ohio, 1981 October 16 (Box 2)
  - Guest appearance, The Estelle Doheny Eye Foundation, Beverly Wilshire Hotel, Los Angeles, California, 1981 October 22 (Box 2)
  - Address, dedication of Hastings College of the Law new library building, San Francisco, California, 1981 October 27 (Box 2)
  - Draft of speech to the American Jewish Congress Annual Dinner at the Hyatt at Union Square, San Francisco, 1981 October 28 (Box 2)
  - Speech, New Trier Township Republican Dinner, Allgauer's, Illinois, 1981 October 29 (Box 2)
  - American Society of Criminology Annual Meeting banquet address, Capitol Hilton Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1981 November 12 (Box 2)
  - "Progress of the Reagan Administration in Domestic and Foreign Affairs: An Overview," remarks, Republican National Committee Executive Board Luncheon, Shoreham Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1981 November 13 (Box 2)
  - Keynote address, Twelfth Annual Symposium of Washington Forum, Hyatt Regency Hotel-Capitol Hill, Washington, D.C., 1981 November 19 (Box 2)
  - Speech, National War College, National Defense University, Fort McNair, Washington, D.C., 1981 November 24 (Box 2)
  - Keynote speech, Society of American Military Engineers, National Defense University, Fort McNair, Washington, D.C., 1981 November 24 (Box 2)
  - Remarks, Joint Meeting of the Inspectors General and Assistant Secretaries for Management, Federal Bureau of Investigation Training Academy, Quantico, Virginia, 1981 November 30 (Box 2)
  - Speech, Joint Meeting of the President's Council on Integrity and Efficiency and the Assistant Secretaries for Management Group, Federal Bureau of Investigation Training Academy, Quantico, Virginia, 1981 November 30 (Box 2)
  - Luncheon address, Annual Conference of the American Society for Public Administration, National Capital Area Chapter, Capitol Hilton Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1981 December 2 (Box 2)
  - Address, National Republican Congressional Committee Leadership Council Meeting, the Four Seasons Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1981 December 3 (Box 2)
  - Keynote speech, Alameda-Contra Costa County Trial Lawyers Association, Claremont Resort, Oakland, California, 1981 December 9 (Box 2)
  - Remarks, East Bay Regional Park and District Arrowhead Marsh dedication ceremony, San Leandro Bay, California, 1981 December 10 (Box 3)
  - Address, Lake Merritt Breakfast Club, Oakland, California, 1981 December 10 (Box 3)
  - Press conference and luncheon address, Commonwealth Club of California, Sheraton Palace Hotel, San Francisco, California, 1981 December 10 (Box 3)
  - Remarks before Junior Statesmen Foundation Gala, Sheraton Palace Hotel, San Francisco, California, 1981 December 11 (Box 3)
  - Keynote address, California School Boards Association - Association of California School Administrators Joint Annual Conference, San Francisco, California, 1981 December 11 (Box 3)
  - Speech, University of Hawaii Law School Dinner, Royal Hawaiian Hotel, Waikiki Beach, Hawaii, 1981 December 14 (Box 3)
  - Interview, Meet the Press, television program of National Broadcasting Company, Washington, D.C., 1982 January 7 (Box 3)
  - Speech, John Tower Dinner, Fairmont Hotel, Dallas, Texas, 1982 January 14 (Box 3)
  - Presentation, Washington Metropolitan Area Corporate Counsel Association, Marriott Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 January 15 (Box 3)
  - Keynote address, Adjutants General Association of the United States Mid-Winter Conference, Opryland Hotel, Nashville, Tennessee, 1982 January 17 (Box 3)
  - Ambassador's roundtable remarks, Foreign Policy Association Madison Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 January 21 (Box 3)
  - Speech, Presidential Inaugural Trust, Sulgrave Club, Washington, D.C., 1982 January 22 (Box 3)
  - Address, Conservative Leadership Conference, Sheraton-Washington Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 January 22 (Box 4)
  - Speech, Shell Oil Company Board of Directors Meeting, Sheraton-Carlton Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 January 28 (Box 4)
  - Remarks, West Point Society of Los Angeles, Los Angeles, California, 1982 February (Box 4)
  - Address, U.S. Chamber of Commerce "Breakfast Bunch," Washington, D.C., 1982 February 4 (Box 4)
  - Address, Prescott Bush Award Dinner, Connecticut, 1982 February 9 (Box 4)
  - Speech, Republican Rally Dinner, New Haven, Connecticut, 1982 February 9 (Box 4)
  - Remarks, Convention II, Inc., banquet, Shoreham Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 February 10 (Box 4)
  - Address, National Capital Area Council of the Boy Scouts of America: Scouter of the Year Award Dinner, Sheraton Washington Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 February 15 (Box 4)
  - Speech, Executive Council on Foreign Relations, State Department, Washington, D.C., 1982 February 17 (Box 4)
  - Press conference, Lincoln Day Dinner for Congressman Del Latta, Archbold, Ohio, 1982 February 20 (Box 4)
  - Keynote address, U.S. Civil Defense Council Mid-Year Conference, Shoreham Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 1 (Box 4)
  - Presentation, Federal Emergency Management Agency, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 1 (Box 4)
  - Remarks, Association for Advanced Life Underwriters Annual Meeting, Capitol Hilton Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 1 (Box 4)
  - Opening address, Congress on the Bible Opening Session, San Diego, California, 1982 March 3 (Box 4)
  - Yale Political Union Washington Symposium, Hotel Harrington, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 10 (Box 4)
  - Keynote address, Foundation for American Communications Conference for Journalists on International Affairs, Washington Hilton Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 10 (Box 4)
  - Featured speaker, National Newspaper Association Government Affairs Conference, Hyatt Regency on Capitol Hill, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 12 (Box 4)
  - Speech, American Business Conference, Inc., Membership Meeting Dinner, Hyatt Regency Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 15 (Box 4)
  - The Media and the Economic Recovery Program speech at the Media Institute Monthly Luncheon Series, Mayflower Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 16 (Box 4)
  - Address, West Point Society of New York, University Club of New York City, New York, 1982 March 23 (Box 4)
  - Speech, Calvin Bullock Forum, New York, 1982 March 23 (Box 4)
  - Remarks, National Health Council, Inc., breakfast briefing, Capitol Hilton, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 26 (Box 4)
  - Speech, Veterans of Foreign Wars Conference, Sheraton Washington Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 29 (Box 5)
  - Address, Forum on "The Reagan Administration," Twenty-first Evans-Novak Political Forum, Madison Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 March 31 (Box 5)
  - Speech, General Counsel's Committee Luncheon, Federal Bar Association, National Lawyers Club, Washington, D.C., 1982 April 2 (Box 5)
  - Speech, Bermuda Bar Association Second Annual Dinner, Sonesta Beach Hotel, Bermuda, 1982 April 3 (Box 5)
  - Speech, Merchants Club, New York City, New York, 1982 April 25 (Box 5)
  - Speech, National Organization of Black Law Enforcement Executives (NOBLE), Washington, D.C., 1982 April 19 (Box 5)
  - Address, Federal Executive Institute Alumni Association Monthly Luncheon, Fort McNair Officers Club, Washington, D.C., 1982 April 22 (Box 5)
  - Presentation, Lutheran House of Studies Symposium, Washington, D.C., 1982 April 23 (Box 5)
  - Remarks, U.S. Chamber of Commerce Annual Meeting, Washington, D.C., 1982 April 26 (Box 5)
  - Address, National Guard Association of California Annual State Conference, Disneyland Hotel, Anaheim, California, 1982 May 1 (Box 5)
  - Remarks, Citizens for Law and Order Annual Meeting, Alameda Naval Air Station, California, 1982 May 1 (Box 5)
  - Guest appearance, This Week with David Brinkley, ABC Television Network, Washington, D.C., 1982 May 9 (Box 5)
  - Commencement address, Valparaiso University, Valparaiso, Indiana, 1982 May 23 (Box 5)
  - Speech, Homer Ferguson Conference on Appellate Advocacy, George Washington University, Washington, D.C., 1982 May 25 (Box 6)
  - "Unlocking America," speech, "Business: The Missing Link In Community Crime Prevention Conference," Plaza Hotel, New York, 1982 May 25 (Box 6)
  - Address, "Brookings Institution Seminar on Setting National Priorities: The 1983 Budget," Brookings Institution, Washington, D.C., 1982 May 26 (Box 6)
  - "The Domestic Foundations of National Security," speech, Army War College, 1982 National Security Seminar, Carlisle Barracks, Pennsylvania, 1982 June 3 (Box 6)
  - Address, National Academy of Public Administration Spring Meeting - Annual Luncheon, Conference Facilities, Du Pont Circle, Washington, D.C., 1982 June 4 (Box 6)
  - Remarks, Federal Emergency Management Agency Annual Awards Ceremony, Washington, D.C., 1982 June 4 (Box 6)
  - Speech, Conference on Judicial Reform, Mayflower Hotel, Washington, D.C., 1982 June 14 (Box 6)
  - Speech, Meeting of the Free Congress Research and Education Foundation, Washington, D.C., 1982 June 15 (Box 6)
  - "The Choice in 1982," luncheon speech, political trip, Cleveland, Ohio, 1982 June 25 (Box 6)
  - Remarks, Chautauqua Institution Second Century Campaign Luncheon, Chautauqua Institution National Affairs Week, Athenaeum Hotel, Chautauqua, New York, 1982 July 1 (Box 7)
  - Interview, Larry King Show, Arlington, Virginia, 1982 July 10 (Box 7)
  - Address, Eighth North American Lutheran Sunday School Convention, Palmer House, Chicago, Illinois, 1982 July 17 (Box 7)
  - Remarks, National District Attorneys' Association, Copley Plaza Hotel, Boston, Massachusetts, 1982 July 20 (Box 7)
  - Presentation, 35th Annual Confederation of Interallied Reserve Officers (CIOR) Congress Ceremony, Fort Meyer, Virginia, 1982 August 9 (Box 7)